<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of the Hungarian War newly published by the most illustrious Michael Apafi, Prince of Transilvania, against His Imperial Majesty, 1682.</title>
            <title>Declaratio belli Hungarici. English</title>
            <author>Transylvania (Principality). Sovereign (1661-1690 : Apafi Mihály I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3526A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875610</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875610</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152176</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152176)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2281:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of the Hungarian War newly published by the most illustrious Michael Apafi, Prince of Transilvania, against His Imperial Majesty, 1682.</title>
                  <title>Declaratio belli Hungarici. English</title>
                  <author>Transylvania (Principality). Sovereign (1661-1690 : Apafi Mihály I)</author>
                  <author>Apafi Mihály I, Prince of Transylvania, 1632-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Grantham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Transylvania (Romania) --  History.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  History --  1526-1683 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  Foreign relations --  Turkey.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  Foreign relations --  Hungary.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152176:1"/>
            <head>THE DECLARATION OF THE Hungarians War, Newly publiſhed by the Moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Michael Apafi,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> againſt his Imperial Majeſty, 1682.</head>
            <head>To the Kings, Princes, Common-wealths of Chriſtendom; to all States and Ranks of the Sacred <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and laſtly to the People of the unfortunate <hi>Pononian,</hi> or <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian</hi> Nation, groaning under the burthen of oppreſſion, to everlaſting memory.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Michael Apafi,</hi> by the Grace of God, Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> Lord of part of the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> Count of <hi>Sic:</hi> do manifeſt and bear teſtimony in ſimplicity and purity of Faith and Truth.</head>
            <p>AFter that by frowning deſtinies, and deſtructive idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Nobles diſcording among themſelves, the enſigns of regal dignity were devolved from Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Hungarion</hi> Blood, to perſons of the <hi>Auſtriack</hi> Family, (whence ſprang the Fountain of our wounds and miſeries) they did endeavour by counſels connected and circling in themſelves, to procure and eſtabliſh to themſelves abſolute and hereditary dominion over <hi>Hungary,</hi> deſtroying and trampling liberty, continued inviolate for ſeveral Ages before.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152176:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Who though they were oblidged by the ſanctity and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſolemn Oath, according to the Foundation of free Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (which, from the very riſe of the Kingdom, was the firſt and fundamental Law amongſt the <hi>Hungarians</hi>) to preſume nothing in prejudice of the Nations Laws and priviledges, did notwithſtanding ſeek out various Pretexts, that by Liberties diſtruction, the Spirits of the Nations Inhabitants ſhould be made bitter; they did eſteem ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and fomenting matter of Diſſention, for engaging more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Souls inclined to Liberty, (diſſatisfactory and repugnant to them) againſt each other, to facilitate their overthrow and ſuppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a miſtery of domineering effectual and ſuitable to their purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Nor did the prepoſterous Luſt of Dominion contain it ſelf in thoſe Limits, but perſons of all Ranks were Vehemently pillaged and oppreſſed by exceſſive Calamities and intolerable rigour, the Barrs of Faith and Solemn Oaths being broak aſunder. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and determinate purpoſe of their intentions was, to evert the Fortreſſes of the Nations Laws and priviledges, by gradual and ingeneous machinations, and thoſe not ſucceeding, by open force, the ſecret Providence of a diſpleaſed. God permitting the ſame; Whither becauſe a fatal period was approaching a moſt Flouriſhing Kingdom, or becauſe the refuſers of due obedience to a Lawful Prince of their own Blood, were to feel the weight of a Strangers Domineering.</p>
            <p>Theſe miſeries received increment by the contempt and diſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the Nations Peers and Nobles, who contrary to the ſtrength of Law, were gradually excluded or removed from Dignities and publick Functions, and ſubjected to inſolent Government, and Dominion of Strangers; ſo by daily growth of injuries, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valancy of force, the ſtate of <hi>Hungary</hi> was ſo far precipatate, that ſcarce a ſhaddow or veſtage of Antient Liberty could be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: whatſomever once appeared high and glorious, was now neglected and trod under Foot, ruine and overthrow was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for all ſuſpect Vertue.</p>
            <p>Petitions and Complaints were no way prevailent, Appeals to Regal fidelity were in vain; will Occupied the Chair of Reaſon, whatſomever they pleaſed, or ſeemed to them expedient, was practiced: Complaints were ſometimes received in ſhow and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but in Conformity to the rule of extravagant Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and for further Torment, returned with vain and irrit Words, and often eluded by <hi>Ludibri</hi> and upbrading reproach.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152176:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Ambition of Governours and Kings Officials, their inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble avarice and Bloody practices of Cruelty did accrew to ſuch a hight, that Men were rendred ſuſpect againſt the King, and Noxious to the publick becauſe of their Riches, hence were they Robbed by moſt wicked pretexts, their Goods divided and dragged from them, either that the Blood-ſuckers might ſatiate their vora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Appetites or the Exchequer a place for pillaging the Poor, and moſt infamous receptickle of Horrid Rapines might be cram'd. Now the congruous and true names of things were baniſhed; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr other mens Goods in reward of Treachery was called Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency; to deſtribute the fortunes of the wandring and illegally exiled amongſt Baſtards, Liberalitie, pardoning of Innocents co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured with the name of Mercy; in ſhort, all things Divine and human was at the diſpoſal of the <hi>Germans:</hi> In the Kingdom was Want Dammage, Diſhonour and a moſt Abominable Scheme of affairs.</p>
            <p>When Souls vigorous and impatient of Servitude, were bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened above meaſure, with thoſe and innumerable injuries, at length the exceſs of Patience inclining to revenge, did betake them ſelves to juſt and allowed Remedies; calling to mind they had choſen a King by free ſuffrages, not a Maſter they endeavoured to reduce the extravagent and indirect manner of Governing to its ordinary Channel.</p>
            <p>A Remedy by War is concluded upon; immediately ſudden meetings, a Soul uniting ſociety ariſing from common haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and loſs of Liberty, together with the juſtneſs of their Cauſe, did animate that moſt Noble Nation to lay hold on neceſſary and juſt Arms, and endeavour reſtitution of now buried Liberty to former ſplendor and integrity, without the ſtain of Rebellion or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, according to the tenour of the Decree of King <hi>Andrew</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> ſurnamed of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The magnanimous <hi>Hero, Stephen Bocskai,</hi> a man of excellent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gene, famous for War-like Vertue and ſagacity, repute more than a private perſon while private, did firſt aſſault this luxureant force, who iritate with exceſſive injuries, with a ſmall number of Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, but great and undaunted reſolution of Soul, oppoſed himſelf to rageing violence, with a high and Heroick ſpirit, aſſaulted a part of the Emperial Army, with happy ſucceſs did rout and chaſe the ſame, and perſuing, his firſt victory did fill the Kingdom
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152176:3"/>and the World with admirable progreſs, having gained the Honour to be by common conſent of the people of <hi>Hungary,</hi> declared Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> and <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and Patron of Liberty, which he did not only revive from the duſt of Death, but did alſo preſcribe due meaſures to the King then Reigning, <hi>viz. Rodul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> the ſecond and his ſucceſſors, Circumſcribing their Power according to the Laws Limitations.</p>
            <p>Now there appeared moſt excellent and conducible proviſion for peace and publick tranquility, moſt ample conditions were ratified in a Treatiſe by which, ſafety, integrity, and ſecurity of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty Civil and Eccleſiaſtick, were aſſured to the Subjects by Regal Faith, and Letters Patents: But not long after, the Inhabitants experienced Hope to be ſalacious, and humane expectation to be founded upon an unſtable bottom; for not long after the Peace, the moſt illuſtrious <hi>Bocskai</hi> paying his laſt debt by his untimely death, did afford ſorrow to the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and a new occaſion for ambition, while almoſt they by the ſame Burial performed Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Solemnity to the Memory of the great Patron of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and their decaying Liberty; a paſſage to be memorate to all poſterity, that as it were by a new Funeral, their lately regenit Liberties were overwhelmed immediately, contrary to Faith and conditions of Peace, occaſions were catched for breaking the late compacts, as if they they had been extorted by force of Arms; which were, notwithſtanding, of free choice and voluntary conſent.</p>
            <p>Which unbridled Licenſe, breach of Faith and ſolemn Oath, the diſcreetly intelligent Freemen of the Nation, ſuſtaining with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſpleaſure, that they might apply new and effectual Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments to reiterate Maladies, did betake themſelves to their Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Priviledge of reſiſting their oppreſſing Kings, and directed their eyes towards the protection of my Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>The Atroſity of moſt exquiſite oppreſſions, and everſion of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges Divine and Humane, did promove the zeal of thoſe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous purpoſes, by which alſo my Anceſtors <hi>Gabriel Betlen</hi> and <hi>George Rakoci</hi> the firſt, a Prince of glorious memory (here I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude double injuries, and a twofold Warr in one compend, to evit the recital of particulars) did imploy all endeavours to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focate an approaching miſchief in its birth, reverberate the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſſure of incumbent violence, and eſteeming the afflictions of a dejected Nation their own, either to mitigate or remove the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152176:3"/>ſame, with deſign always to compreſs inſolent and extravagant dominion within the boundaries of Laws and Priviledges, leaſt Liberty and Religions final overthrow ſhould tend to a moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Kingdoms total everſion, and damnifying prejudice of all Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>Arms are again Levied for the Defence of that moſt righteous Cauſe, ſo countenanced with Bleſſings from Heaven, the <hi>Auſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack</hi> Kings frighted with increment of Arms and unexpected ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, of their own accord propoſed, and did conclude a Peace, ratifying the ſame by Faith and publick Chartour; but this Peace, confirmed and regiſtrate in the houdge bulk of Two Treatiſes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded not to <hi>Hungary</hi> expected tranquility, or continuing Peace: The Kings in ſuch reſpits did rather lay hold on all occaſions, that in a ſtate of imaginary and fraudulent Peace, they might, by their accuſtamary infatuating Machinations, infect and divide the minds of Peers and Nobles, which they could not infringe by force and War.</p>
            <p>It were tedious, and more than neceſſary to memorate in a prolix gradation calamities of former times, which, ſince com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the monuments of Hiſtories, I ſhall not recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; laying aſide therefore the precedent, I ſhall ſhortly relate the grievouſneſs of the preſent, that the whole world may judge and cognoſs the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who have ſuſtained violence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, are ſtript of their whole liberties contrary to Regal Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and Faith, the contents of Charter and publick Laws, have taken up juſt, warrantable and allowed Arms.</p>
            <p>It muſt of neceſſity be granted, and ought not to be reflected upon without intimate and hearty ſenſe of grief, that his now Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Imperial Kingly Majeſty, immediately after his being inſtalled in the Government by free ſuffrage, according to the ancient uſe and cuſtom, treading the footſteps of his Predeceſſors, did decline from legal procedure in Government, to burthenſom and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute domineering: In the whole Tract of his Government, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted nothing of the cuſtomary inveterate endeavours of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging Liberty, and nothing but what pleaſed was granted to Addreſſers and Supplicants according to publick Law. An Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage of Liberty, and oſtentation of Regal Clemency, portended Slavery to the Malecontents.</p>
            <p>In this ſtate of expiring and vehemently depreſſed Liberty,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152176:4"/>there wanted not highly generous Spirits among the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> thorowly grieved with the fraudulent machinations and counſels practiſed to the overthrow of the publick, who modeſtly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the violence and breach of publick Faith, but with more zeal than ſucceſs; for as his Majeſty had received the ſupream Honour of Government, impared and deflowred by others, and ought according to Faith and Obligation to have reſtored the ſame to former Luſtre and Integrity, ſo managed he the ſame according to Luſt and Illimited Dominion.</p>
            <p>Hence from reſpect and obedience due to Regal Majeſty (of which the people of <hi>Hungary</hi> have ſtill been moſt obſervant) mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation of rigourous Maſter-ſhip, was firſt eſſayed by Addreſſes and Supplications; but while neither complaints, nor volumes of grievances, often compoſed and rejected, could put any ſtop to the currant of inordinate Power, a plaiſter for Wounds was to be found out by the Sword, which a publick Law doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Lawful and Juſt; and to be laid hold on when any of the Kings, not obſerving the true Ballance of Ordinary Power, do proceed to a prepoſtrous Licentiouſneſs of domineering, contrary to the Nations manifeſt Laws and priviledges, and the intereſt of the Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>And I heartily wiſh the Arms once taken up in defence of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, had been continued in better Order, and with more vigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous endeavours; it had been more Glorious, more Vertuous, to have recovered the over-clouded ſplendor of Liberty, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and generous Achievements, than be ſubjugate to moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful Slavery by too much Credulity and fatal diſcord.</p>
            <p>But an Inclination to Diſſention, natural to the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, together with the Word and Promiſes of His Sacred Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Kingly Majeſty, which moſt effectualy bewitched them, did ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly put a ſtop to ſo conſiderable Commencements.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as it was notified to the Court at <hi>Vienna,</hi> that thirteen Counties had Levied Arms for recovering their Liberties, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by an exquiſite artifice, for renting their minds, Letters were directed to the foreſaid Counties, in which Pardon was granted to all, repenting their defection, ſhould deſert the <hi>Racocian</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in due obedience to their King: Moreover it was added, that already committed delinquencies ſhould be liable to no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152176:4"/>by Law or Judicatory whatſomever; that all ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued without hurt or Damage in Life, Liberty and Fortune, in poſſeſſion of moveables and immoveables; at the report of this immunity publickly ratified by Regal Faith, their minds were rent affunder to the loſs of vigour and motion, and laying down their Arms with indiſcretion, they again betook themſelves to Peace of too ſhort continuance, eſteeming a ſpacious door of ſuperaboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant benignity, opened to all who pleaſed to enter, who indeed were preſerved for a more ſecure Vengeance for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for ſome forfeited their Lives, others their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and ſome were puniſhed by perpetual Impriſonment; this never enough to be lamented inconſtancy, did open a Gate; and furniſh the Imperialiſts with ſufficient occaſions to effectuate all their purpoſes; who liberate from fear, under the conduct of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Sporkius</hi> invaded <hi>Hungary,</hi> and ruſhing into the Heart of the Nation without loſs of Blood or Man, did ſeize Towns, Caſtles, and Fortreſſes; neither were there any to reſiſt, the people being ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cheated with the promiſed benignity.</p>
            <p>By theſe means they did proceed to all manner of afflictions, rapines and Libidinous baſeneſs, which the unbridled Soldiers committed every where, contrary to the tenour of the foreſaid Letters, and Regal ſecurity; Churches were abuſed and pulled down, Caſtles demoliſhed, Noble-mens Courts everted, and the Nobillity, who inconſiderately confided in promiſed Oblivion, drag'd to Judgement at <hi>Poſonia;</hi> yet many of the more diſcreet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing fraudulant machinations couched under the mask of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Clemency and Grace, did evit prepared ſhares, betaking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to my protection in this Province.</p>
            <p>The report of ſo lamentable calamity and unexpected altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtruck me with grievous and unſpeakable aſtoniſhment; and becauſe I underſtood this ſtorm would break out in tempeſts moſt dangerous and prejudicial to the Chriſtian World, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, from an upright and ſincere intention, I ſent my Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador to his Sacred Imperial Majeſty, repreſenting the hazard which might follow the Application of too corroſive Medicaments to this Malady, and that remiſs and mollifying Plaiſters were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible, that Souls might be engaged to hope and confide in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Clemency, leaſt driven to diſpair, they be prompted to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of dangerous conſequence, to <hi>Hungary</hi> and all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152176:5"/>But this my propoſal again and again reiterate, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely upright endeavours for publick advantage were heard, but with difficulty, and returned without a ſuitable or deſired anſwer; the luſt of abſolute dominion had taken deeper roots than could be pluckt up by words and perſwaſions.</p>
            <p>The compleat progreſs, and all the actings in the Kingdom did ſavour violence, not Kingly Government; nothing required ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law procured, no mans ſtate ſecure, delinquency at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Riches: Neither now was the proceedure gradual, but with precepitate rage to all manner of affliction. It evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared an occaſion of converting a free Kingdom to a hereditary, long ſought after, was now voraciouſly ſnatched. Immediately Violence is practiſed, the glory of liberty undone, the Peers and Patriots of Law trod under foot, the Nobility baniſhed their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors habitations, their goods confiſcate; dignities, honours, and places of publick truſt conferred on Strangers in prejudice of the Kingdoms conſtitutions; moreover a Council of rigorous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition inſtitute againſt liberties aſſertors, or any ſuſpect oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to their illegal endeavours; three Counts judged by a moſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal Proceſs, and murdered by the hands of bloody Execution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, a memorable inſtance to the World of their ſavage cruelty; but all this was defective to ſatiate revenge, for the miſery of Orphants was augmented, by redacting the Children of the ſlain and baniſhed to Beggery.</p>
            <p>Their ſeaſing the Churches of the reformed was an acceſſary of this Tragedy, in which Fury and exceſſive madneſs did rage ſo impetuouſly, that men might have imagined they waged War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt houſes ſet apart for pious uſes, and the Walls had been Guilty of Rebellion; ſuddenly the Miniſters were thruſt out from their Congregations and expelled their native Land, others forced by the terror of threats to give ſecurity no more to Preach, did obtain their Lives and Liberties to depart the Nation, and many, as piacular Sacrifices, were condemned to the Gallies (a horrid and ever to be abominate preſedent, that their leading an anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and miſerable Life, they might be conſumed with grief, want of cleanly accomodation, hard Labours and Hunger.</p>
            <p>A violent Torrent of Perſecution, and curſed Tyrannizing over Conſciences went on a pace, no Marriage to be ſolemnized, nor Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme adminiſtred, but by <hi>Roman</hi> Miniſters; men drag'd by Force
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152176:5"/>and Arms to Maſſes and Proceſſions every where, endeavourers to draw back, were affected with exceſſive penalties and pecuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Mulcts.</p>
            <p>Neither were women exempt from danger, who not charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with leſe Majeſty, were accuſed for tears; it was a treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, and of dangerous conſequence to ſigh under miſery, and weeping over the Sentenced by Death, a thing diſcharged.</p>
            <p>Money was extorted privately and publickly from the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Commons, by various Stratagems, and feigned Names, Gariſons removed and ſetled, Laws irrogate at pleaſure, Rapines, Plunderings, and innumerable Oppreſſions over all.</p>
            <p>The Exiled Lords, provoked by theſe and other Inexplicable Injuries, brought to the Precipiſe of final overthrow of Life and Fortune; deſtitute of all help from Chriſtians, and perceiving no hope of mitigating His Majeſty, did reſolve in this extream neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to betake themſelves to the benignity of the Illuſtrious <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman,</hi> Soveraignity, and implore his Protection againſt moſt unjuſt violence, for the relief of the Kingdom, and ſafety of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Innocents. Neither was their reſolutions in vain; their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts ware admitted with ſmall difficulty; and whom a hard Lot, and extream Rigour, had rendred Exiles, the Generoſity and Condeſcention of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Soveraignity did furniſh with refuge, ſecurity and means for Suſtenance. Often are the works of the Divine Soveraign ſo ordered, that ſudden puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment overtaketh rageing cruelty, when ſecure in ſucceſs it ſelf; leaſt ſtraying ſhould at any time be removed from the wicked, or hope utterly detained from afflicted vertue.</p>
            <p>I know many do miſconſtruct this Act of Extream Neceſſity, and prepoſtrouſly ſlander the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Nation, as dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, and making defection from Chriſtians; but ſuch are either ignorant of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Liberty, according to fundamental conſtitution, or too active promoters of the <hi>Auſtriack</hi> intereſt.</p>
            <p>It aught to be conſidered, the <hi>Auſtriack</hi> Kings were advanced to Crown and Scepter by the ſuffrages of a free Election, (the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152176:6"/>moſt ancient and righteous form of Government amongſt the <hi>Hungarians</hi>) and obleadged by Faith, and ſolemn Oath (which ſolemnity, according to cuſtom was performed under the open Heavens) to maintain the Nations Liberties; from this Faith and Solemn Oath ariſeth a formal and true obligation, not only ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for exercing Government-according to the preſcript of Laws, and tenour of Regal Charter, but doth authorize the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate of the Kingdom, as the Guardian of Liberty, with the Inhabitants, to contradict and reſiſt the King, degenerating from ordinary and allowed power, to ſavageneſs and unjuſt Licence of domineering; therefore in caſe of deſpairing reduction to due meaſures, Liberty was not annihilate, nor the priviledge of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing protection from whomſoever, even from the <hi>Ottoman,</hi> as a neighbouring Monarch.</p>
            <p>Many years are now paſt ſince this unfortunate Kingdom, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced betwixt two Potentates, cut ſhort by the one, and trod un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot by the other, hath exhibit a moſt lamentable Tragedy to the World, the firſt never levied War againſt it, nor laid aſide Arms without increment to his Empire, and the diminition of this counter-mure, whence it hath been almoſt equally ſubjected to its moſt potent Neighbour. Seeing then this Kingdom bordering on either ſide with a moſt potent Monarch is neceſſitate to ſuſtain their firſt aſſault and Force, and that the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> hath hitherto ſought or intended nothing by Governing, but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the everſion of its Liberties, eſpecially his now Imperial Majeſty hath redacted a free People of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves liberally moderate; to diſhonourable puſillanimity and moſt miſerable condition, whom deſparation, efficacious in ſtraits and intricacies, did Arm, and ſince for the time of Eleven years Baniſhment, they could ſee no relaxation or hope for removing oppreſſion, it did ſeem more conducing in the caſe of extream and inevitable neceſſity, to betake themſelves to the protection of a moſt potent Prince, and make uſe of his help, than inevitably precepitate the remainder of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Neither are the <hi>Hungarians</hi> the firſt who have implored <hi>Ottoman</hi> aſſiſtance in their defence: <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Fredirick,</hi> Brethren to the King of <hi>Caſtil,</hi> in the time of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 4th, when aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152176:6"/>with the Sons of <hi>Conradus,</hi> did call the <hi>Saracens</hi> by Sea and Land, not to defend their Country, but to expell the <hi>French</hi> from <hi>Italy. Maximillian</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> that he might repell Force carried on againſt him, but eſpecially that he might deſtroy the <hi>Venecian</hi> Common-wealth, was active to procure the <hi>Turks</hi> aſſiſtance; <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt of <hi>France,</hi> when he perceived the ambition and dangerous Power of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, did not queſtion the accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing help from the <hi>Turk;</hi> neither was it unglorious in our time, for the famous State of <hi>Polonia</hi> to call the <hi>Tartars</hi> to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Let therefore the Chriſtian World judge by the foreſaid Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whether the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Nation, of a moſt free conſtitution, priviledged by their fundamental Laws, with a ſhare of Supream Power, reſerving, in conferring Government, natural Liberty, exempt from Regal Authority (<hi>viz.</hi> to reſiſt the King in a caſe) hath acted iniquiouſly in ſubmitting themſelves to the illuſtrious <hi>Ottoman</hi> Soveraignty, engadging by Imperial Faith, the reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Liberty, the ſecurity of Religion, Life and Honour, and maintenance of all Priviledges.</p>
            <p>As for my ſelf who am by off-ſpring and deſcent a <hi>Hungarian,</hi> originally the ſame with that Nation, and do acknowledge my ſelf to be erected to a Princely Throne of an <hi>Hungarian</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by God the founder of Kingdoms, and placed as it were on a Watch-Tower, to manage the defence of Civil and Religious Priviviledges, and repell, according to my Power, Injuries in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred againſt a moſt free people, without evidence of any juſt Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe cauſes and reſpects prompted me to lay hold on Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Neceſſary Arms, to reſtore Liberty, and reduce oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed exiles: Therefore let no diſcreet and ſober perſon admire my undertaking the Righteous cauſe of a moſt renowned Nation, eſpecially of my own Blood. My ſcope is, that an once moſt Flouriſhing Kingdom may be by the help of divine Benignity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to deſired Tranquillity, and a moſt free Nation to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Liberty of their Anceſtors; it is moſt Righteous and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to Reaſon, to defend Liberty violate againſt Faith, right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152176:7"/>granted by expreſs Laws, It is juſt to undertake a defenſive War for Friends and Relations violently afflicted, the Univerſal relation of Mankind were a reaſon of it ſelf ſufficient for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſſiſtance; neither is the right of Humane Society ſuffocate, when Kings exerce injuries approveable by no Righteous and Diſcreet perſon, againſt free Subjects.</p>
            <p>Moreover I admoniſh and exhort, yea, I beſeech and obteſt all Ranks in <hi>Hungary</hi> to joyn with me in Righteous and Pious Arms, for endeavouring the reduction of Liberties, Glory to former ſplendor, by Glorious Achievements, and concording Unity: Let the vertue of our Predeceſſors poſſeſs our Souls, who with their Blood, who with their Lives did defend their Liberties. There is need of conſtant and vigorous reſolution in affairs of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and what is remaining muſt be committed to Divine diſpoſal, which hath Crowned by-paſt undertakings and exploits for recovering Liberty with moſt Bleſſed events.</p>
            <p>Here is no private controverſy nor queſtion about <hi>Romiſh</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which hath the advantage of the ſame Priviledge with the Evangelick or reformed, our diſpute is for our Country, our Lives, our Fortunes, our Honours, and the whole Nations Glory. They are Hunting unjuſt Dominion, your Blood and Fortunes; perſue your Liberty, which no good man, no vertuous man, no noble or generous man will loſe but with his Life.</p>
            <p>For my part, I am conſcious of Human frailty, nor am I without conſideration of Fortunes force, I acknowledge all my undertakings ſubject to a Thouſand various incidents, but having ſatisfaction and ſecurity of Conſcience in ſerenity and compoſure of Spirit, by Gods aſſiſtance I undertake your defence, propoſing nothing to my ſelf but intreſt of publick ſafety; without heſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I expect proſperous progreſs, and a Bleſſed period.</p>
            <p>But if any ſhall betake themſelves to the adverſe party, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their Countries overthrow, their own temerity, treſpaſs and error ſhall be liable, not I, to any cenſure, if deſerved puniſhment ſhall accompany their contumacy: But I hope, and am confident, all ranks and conditions ſhall direct their counſels,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152176:7"/>thoughts and undertakings, to the ſafety, enlargement and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſt of their Country. By Blood our Anceſtors at firſt did come to peaceable poſſeſſion of their Liberties, which ſince by blood hath been ſecured and maintained, and now remains its vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and recovery from oppreſſion and everſion, to be attained and effectuated by Blood.</p>
            <p>I ſhall be ſufficiently remunerate, aboundantly honoured, if in injoying Liberty, I ſhall ſee my Countries relief; or in caſe of overthrow, my right hand patronizing Liberty, ſhall fall among the Carcaſſes of my Country-men, and my Soul freed from guilt, be removed to a better Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord God of Hoſts, the Juſt and Omnipotent God, Bleſs from the Higheſt our ſincere and lawful endeavours; be the orderer of all our actings and counſels, diſpoſe and engadge minds alienate and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentient to ſincere concord; confirm the ſtrong, encourage the faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, effectuate the undertaking and terminating of all may tend to the everlaſting Glory of his Name, the reſtitution of overturned Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, the peace and tranquility of an afflicted People, to the private and publick felicity of all and every one.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152176:8"/>
            <head>A true Coppy of the Compact and Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, betwixt the Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Male-coontents.</head>
            <p>THe great Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> upon the following con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions conſtitute, and to be performed on both Parts, hath received in protection, the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who have ſuffered extream violence.</p>
            <p>If the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> rent from the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> ſhall become Tributary, ſhall yearly pay the ſame too, and ever continue in Faith and Obedience towards the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Port</hi> (or Court) which the <hi>Hungarians</hi> oblidge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to perform, Hoſtages being yearly to be ſent to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Port, for the ratification of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi> hath bound himſelf by Oath, to reſtore the <hi>Hungarians</hi> to former Liberty by ſtrong Hands, to repell all violence which may be carried on againſt them by others, and to protect them.</p>
            <p>Above all, that he ſhall exact no tribute from the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians,</hi> until the affairs of <hi>Hungary</hi> be reduced to good condition, all Tumults being appeaſed</p>
            <p>That he ſhall draw to himſelf no Town or Fortreſs of the <hi>Hungarians;</hi> that he ſhall diſturb none in their Liberty Eccleſiaſtick nor Pollitick; that he ſhall allow unto all, the free Exerciſe of their Religion; that he ſhall give Power to erect and repair Churches, Schools, and Parioch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; and to chooſe a Prince of their own Nation, whom
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152176:8"/>they ſhall judge ſufficient, the ſuffrages of the Nations Inhabitants agreeing thereto, no Forrain, beings to be forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly obtruded.</p>
            <p>All this is contain'd in the <hi>Ach-nam</hi> of the great Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the <hi>Turks,</hi> that is: in the Obligatory Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters given to the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> corroborate by his own Hand and the Authentick Seal Imperial, which the preſent Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> hath with himſelf, as to whom, the whole affair of the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary</hi> is committed, to be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by open War, or pacification with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Grantham.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
